<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-26T14:11:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mahesh Yadav</title><subtitle>personal description</subtitle><author><name>Mahesh Yadav</name><email>mahesh27dx@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Phase separation in biology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/Phase-separation-in-biology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phase separation in biology" /><published>2023-03-06T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-03-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/Phase-separation-in-biology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/Phase-separation-in-biology/">&lt;p&gt;Cellular compartments and organelles organize biological matter. Most well-known organelles are separated by a membrane boundary from their surrrounding milieu. There are also many so-called membraneless organelles and recent studies suggest that these organelles, which are supramolecular assemblies of proteins and RNA molecules, from via protein&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mahesh Yadav</name><email>mahesh27dx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="-Research" /><category term="-" /><category term="Publish" /><category term="-" /><category term="Article" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html">Cellular compartments and organelles organize biological matter. Most well-known organelles are separated by a membrane boundary from their surrrounding milieu. There are also many so-called membraneless organelles and recent studies suggest that these organelles, which are supramolecular assemblies of proteins and RNA molecules, from via protein</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discrete error and convergence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/error-convergenve/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discrete error and convergence" /><published>2023-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/error-convergenve</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/error-convergenve/">&lt;p&gt;I was asked a question today about a typical way to present the error between a numerical scheme and an exact solution, and the convergence of the method. I will demonstrate one method that is typically used based on the $L_{2}$-norm of the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the ODE
\(\frac{dx}{dt} = x(t) \qquad x(0) = 1\)
which has the analytic solution&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mahesh Yadav</name><email>mahesh27dx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Research" /><category term="Publish" /><category term="Article writing" /><summary type="html">I was asked a question today about a typical way to present the error between a numerical scheme and an exact solution, and the convergence of the method. I will demonstrate one method that is typically used based on the $L_{2}$-norm of the norm.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Art of Action or Work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2022/12/The%20Art%20of%20Action%20or%20Work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art of Action or Work" /><published>2022-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2022/12/art-of-action</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2022/12/The%20Art%20of%20Action%20or%20Work/">&lt;p&gt;In this world outside all living beings constantly working. Everybody’s ambition is to excel, but despite all honest efforts, some achieve, many never achieve. The temptation of average human being is to condemn someone to his failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a secret of achievements. Renouncing all your physical and mental activities to an alter. How?? by mere thinking. In order to contantly work with dynamism, everyone needs a alter. The alter could be anything like ambitions, family etc. “higher the alter, greater the inspiration”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actions performed through attachments and desires are renounced the moment we take away from the action the ego-centeric and selfish stink. A serpent is dangerous only as long as its fangs are not removed. The moment these are taken out it becomes a tame creature incapable of harming anyone. Similarly, action gives rise to bondage only when it is performed with a heart laden with selfish desires. Actions perfomed by without desires are not actions at all, in as much as they are incapable of producing any painful reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is it sufficient that we renounce thus all wrong actions, but we have also to make a few adjustments in our inner instruments. These two terms are “without hope” and “without ego”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WITHOUT HOPE&lt;/strong&gt; Hope is “the expectation of a happening that is yet to manifest and mature in a future period of time”. Whatever be the hope, it belongs not to the present; it refers to a period of time not yet born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WITHOUT EGO&lt;/strong&gt; Our ego-centeric concepts of ourselves is nothing but “a bundle of happenings and achievements of ours which took place, or were gained, in the past moments”. Ego is, therefore “the shadow of past” and it has an existent reality only with reference to the dead moments of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If hope is thus the child of the unborn future, ego is the lingering memory of a dead past. To revel in ego and hope is an attempt on our part to live, either with the dying moments of the past or with the unborn moments of the future. All the while, the tragedy is that we miss ‘present’, which is the only noble chance that is given to us to advance. Therfore, to act renouncing both hope and ego, and this is indeed a primary instruction on how to pour the best that is in us into the present, blockading all unintelligent and thoughtless dissipation of our inner-personality-energies in the ‘past’ and ‘future’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The instructions are so exhaustive in vision, and complete in its minutest details, that the stanza under review should be surprise even to the best of our moder psychologists. Even though the technique so far advised can, and does, avoid all wastage of energy among the funeral pyres of the dying moments and in the wombs of unborn time, yet, there is a chance for the man of action to wasting his potentialities in the very ‘present’. This generally comes through our inborn nature to get ourselves unnecessarily over-anxious during our present activities. This feverish anxiety is indicated by ‘fear’. The advice is to renounce all actions to an alter and getting rid of both hope and selfishness, must act, free from all mental fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;headings-are-cool&quot;&gt;Headings are cool&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;you-can-have-many-headings&quot;&gt;You can have many headings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arent-headings-cool&quot;&gt;Aren’t headings cool?&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name>Mahesh Yadav</name><email>mahesh27dx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="philosophy" /><category term="personal improvement" /><summary type="html">In this world outside all living beings constantly working. Everybody’s ambition is to excel, but despite all honest efforts, some achieve, many never achieve. The temptation of average human being is to condemn someone to his failure.</summary></entry></feed>